<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Festival App</string>

    <string name="sinulog">Sinulog Festival</string>
    <string name="aswang">Aswang Festival</string>
    <string name="atiatihan">Ati-atihan Festival</string>
    <string name="bonokbonok">Bonok bonok Festival</string>
    <string name="dinagyang">Dinagyang Festival</string>
    <string name="hermosa">Hermosa Festival</string>
    <string name="kaamulan">Kaamulan Festival</string>
    <string name="kadayawan">Kadayawan Festival</string>
    <string name="kagayan">Kagay-an Festival</string>
    <string name="kuraldal">Kuraldal Festival</string>
    <string name="lanzones">Lanzones Festival</string>
    <string name="masskara">Masskara Festival</string>
    <string name="naliyagan">Naligayan Festival</string>
    <string name="obando">Obando Festival</string>
    <string name="pahiyas">Pahiyas Festival</string>
    <string name="bangus">Bangus Festival</string>
    <string name="pintados">Pintados Festival</string>
    <string name="pintaflores">Pintaflores Festival</string>
    <string name="sandugo">Sandugo Festival</string>
    <string name="sarakiki">Sarakiki Hadang Festival</string>
    <string name="moriones">Moriones Festival</string>
    <string name="tuna">Tuna Festival</string>



    <string name="sinulog_description">Sinulog comes from the Cebuano adverb sulog which is \'like water current movement\' which proficiently describes the forward-backward movement of the Sinulog dance. Traditionally, the dance consists of two steps forward and one step backward, done to the sound of the drums. The dance is  classified into Sinulog-base, Free-Interpretation, and recently a Latin Category, which most people have argued that it had nothing to do with Sinulog tradition. Candle vendors at the Basilica continue to perform the traditional version of the dance when lighting a candle for the customer, usually accompanied by songs in the native language.</string>
    <string name="aswang_description">Aswang Festival is a culturally significant and controversial celebration in Roxas City, Capiz intended to change the negative connotation attached to the province popularly called domain of aswang by turning the monster into Capiz\' premier attraction. This annual festivity runs towards the end of October, in time for the yearly observation of All Saints Day or undas in the Philippines. It has been commonly known as the local version of American Halloween celebrations.</string>
    <string name="atiatihan_description">A 1200 A.D. event explains the origins of the festival. A group of 10 Malay chieftains called Datus, fleeing from the island of Borneo settled in the Philippines, and were granted settlement by the Ati people, the tribes of Panay Island. Datu Puti, Makatunaw\'s chief minister made a trade with the natives and bought the plains for a golden salakot, brass basins and bales of cloth. They gave a very long necklace to the wife of the Ati chieftain. Feasting and festivities followed soon after.</string>
    <string name="bonokbonok_description">Surigao is home to the Mamanwa ethnic tribe. Their dances are showcased in a local festival called "Bonok-Bonok", held at the feast of San Nicolas de Tolentino which is held annually on September 10. The Bonok-Bonok depicts the native folks\' merry-making to show gratitude to God for bountiful harvest and good health.</string>
    <string name="dinagyang_description">The root word is dagyang. In Ilonggo, it means to make happy.Dinagyang is the present progressive word of the Ilonggo word,meaning making merry or merry-making. A religious and culturalactivity, it is a celebration of Ilonggos whose bodies arepainted with black in effect to imitate the black, small andslender Negritos who are the aborigines of Panay. The warriorsare dressed in fashionable and colorful Aeta costumes and danceartistically and rhythmically with complicated formations alongwith the loud thrashing and sound of drums.</string>
    <string name="hermosa_description">The Zamboanga La Hermosa Festival embedded in Zamboanga’s rich history of devotion to the Nuestra Señora del Pilar that is supplemented by rich legends. In the Spanish Era, Zamboanga was an integral part of Spanish Colonization. In 1635, the Spaniards built a fort in Zamboanga named \'Real Fuerza de San Jose in Brgy. Zone IV area to secure them against the attacks of the moro warriors. Spaniards held the city as a seat of government and became the cultural center of the south, and was deeply seated in Hispanic heritage and tradition.</string>
    <string name="kaamulan_description">Kaamulan Festival is an ethnic cultural festival held annually in Malaybalay City, Bukidnon in the Philippines from the second half of February to March 10, the anniversary date of the foundation of Bukidnon as a province in 1917. It is held to celebrate the culture and tradition of the seven ethnic tribal groups—Bukidnon, Higaonon, Talaandig, Manobo, Matigsalug, Tigwahanon and Umayamnon—that originally inhabit the province. It is the only ethnic festival in the Philippines. </string>
    <string name="kadayawan_description">Kadayawan festival is honor by the second religion festival it is known filipinos and they are related known as filipino religion festival the kadayawan festival was honored in January 24 and it was raised by the igorots in 1996 together with the filipino as the multi-cultural peoples who join to raise the kadayawan festival.Kadayawan Festival is known being a bounty and diversity of our nature and culture.</string>
    <string name="kagayan_description">The Higalaay Festival (formerly known as Kagay-an Festival, then to Higalaay Kagay-an Festival in 2014) is a festival held each year in Cagayan de Oro, Philippines, every 28th day of August, celebrating the feast day of St. Augustine - patron saint of the city. Higalaay Festival means "Friendship Festival", which the word "Higalaay" comes from the Cebuano word "higala" (friend; chum; pal) which was regarded from what the city of Cagayan de Oro is being tagged, the City of Golden Friendship.</string>
    <string name="kuraldal_description">On the 6th of January, Pampanga’s own version of  the fertility festival in Obando, Bulacan is held in Sasmuan town’s Kuraldal.
        At the end of the 8:00 p.m. High Mass usually concelebrated by the archbishop and other priests, brass bands signal the start of all-night swaying, jumping, dancing festivities around the image of the town’s patron, St. Lucy, in procession snaking through the narrow streets of the poblacion.
        It is believed – as in the Obando rites – that barren women who participate in the festivities invariably get pregnant.
        The festivities end whence they started – at the parish church – to the song “Santa Lucia.”</string>
    <string name="lanzones_description">Lanzones Festival is held every third week of October and it is a four day grand celebration of the lanzones fruit. The most important livelihood in Camiguin is lanzones. It is when a lot of tourists come to witness the joyous Lanzones festival. Lanzones is one of the major fruit producers in the Philippines. Lanzones is a tropical fruit that grows extravagantly on the north-central coast of Mindanao. Lanzones has a pale brown skin and sweet translucent flesh. It is said that the sweetest lanzones in the Philippines comes from Camiguin. The town of Mambajao in Camiguin celebrated its annual festival called Lanzones Festival together with its harvest in the month of October. </string>
    <string name="masskara_description">The Masskara Festival through the years gives the people of Negros, as well as local and foreign visitors, a chance to drinkand be merry for 20 days. Originally designed to show the hardships of the people of Negros, the Masskara Festival has become a tool of escapism and a way to generate revenues for big business. It has indeed come a long way, and it is clear that the path turn away from the progressive goal. </string>
    <string name="moriones_description">The term "Moriones" was concocted by the media in the 60s, but local inhabitants have kept the original term, "Moryonan". Many practitioners are farmers and fishermen who engage in this age-old tradition as a vow of penance or thanksgiving. Legend has it that Longinus pierced the side of the crucified Christ. The blood that spurted forth touched his blind eye and fully restored his sight. This miracle converted Longinus to Christianity and earned the ire of his fellow centurions. The re-enactment reaches its climax when Longinus is caught and beheaded.</string>
    <string name="naliyagan_description">Naliyagan Festival held at Naliyagan Plaza, a space inside the Government Center designated as the place for official celebration in the province as well as the venue for official programs. Here, all the indigenous natives of the entire river valley of Agusan del Sur converge to display their dances, songs, products both agricultural and cottage industries, novelties intricately handmade displaying their glorious past of the natives.</string>
    <string name="obando_description">Obando has hosted this festival since pre-Spanish times. The festival is also mentioned by the country’s national hero, Jose Rizal, in one of his epic novels Noli Me Tangere. Obando, a small town in Bulacan, has held to this age-old tradition of Fertility Dances to the present day and has attracted a lot of tourists the world round.</string>
    <string name="pahiyas_description">Pahiyas means “decor” and the May 15th festival showcases a street of houses adorned with fruits, vegetables, agricultural products, handicrafts and kiping, a decoration made from rice flour, which afterwards can be grilled or fried for eating. The houses compete to be declared the best decorated. Tourists visit Lucban every year in May to see the decoration of the houses. There is also a procession for the saint that concludes at the town’s beautiful church.</string>
    <string name="bangus_description">Bangus Festival, first celebrated in 2002, was the brainchild of former mayor Benjamin S. Lim, who wished to emphasize the local bangus industry and promote Dagupan as the Bangus Capital of the World. Initially a part of the thanksgiving festival Pista\'y Dayat, Bangus Festival developed into a two-week socio-economic program of activities that highlights the city\'s top produce.
The festival commences with the lighting of 1,000 barbecue grills lined up to cook thousands of bangus, which stretches up to two kilometers. This also serves as a competition for hundreds of cooks, whose dishes are not only judged by the grilling but through whipping up the tastiest and most creative way of serving bangus. The contest was eventually called “101 Ways to Cook Bangus” and won for the city a recognition in the Guinness Book of World Records for the longest barbecue in 2003.
Aside from the grilling challenge, the festivity showcases a bangus eating contest, a search for the biggest and heaviest bangus, the Gilon-gilon dancing festival, the Pigar-pigar festival, the Halo-halo festival, and the Bangusan street party, where several local and Manila-based bands perform along Jose R. De Venecia Expressway Extension.</string>
    <string name="pintados_description">The Pintados Festival or Pintados-Kasadyaan Festival is annually celebrated on the 29th of June in Tacloban City, Leyte, to honor the Señor Santo Niño or Holy Child. The festival\'s highlights include the Leyte Kasadyaan Festival of Festivals, the 17th Pintados Festival Ritual Dance Presentation, and the Pagrayhak Grand Parade. In the Visayan dialect, "Kasadyaan" means "merriment and jollity."</string>
    <string name="pintaflores_description">Nowadays, the Pintaflores Festival is one of the most popular street dancing festivals in the region. Held every November 3 – 5, it’s a blend of dances with various functions: from simple rhythmic dances to battles between good and evil.
        The festival’s highlight is the dance ritual performed by townsfolk at the San Carlos City Auditorium. This includes dancers who’s faces, arms, bodies, and legs are painted with flowers as well as a human flower formation incorporated in each performance. </string>
    <string name="sandugo_description">The Sandugo Festival is an annual historical celebration that takes place every year in Tagbilaran City on the island of Bohol in the Philippines. This festival commemorates the Treaty of Friendship between Datu Sikatuna, a chieftain in Bohol, and Spanish conquistador Miguel López de Legazpi. This 16th-century peace treaty occurred on March 16, 1565 through a blood compact or "sandugo".
        The Sandugo Festival is held every July. The Tagbilaran City Charter Day on July 1 kicks-off the month-long festival with a holy mass, diana, motorcade and program sponsored by the City Government of Tagbilaran. Among the major activities during the month is the Miss Bohol Sandugo Beauty Pageant, and the Sandugo Street Dancing Competition which is usually held on the 3rd or 4th Sunday of July, and organized by the Bohol Sandugo Foundation, Inc. (BSFI).
    </string>
    <string name="sarakiki_description">Sarakiki is a local term apparently referring to premeditated or frenzied movements which means to allure, to draw with, to attract or exercise attraction, to entice, or to win. By its pre-colonial denotation, it means to praise, extol, or eulogize spirits of gods. The word does not only ascribe to the ritual or hadang as an activity to gratify the gods, but likewise hadang as the offering or the sacrifice.</string>
    <string name="tuna_description">The week-long celebration features different events and activities focusing on the tuna industry of the province. Among these are the annual Tuna Congress, the Tuna Fiesta Carnival, the Tuna Culinary Skills Competition, the Sashimi Night, the Fish Dance Competition, Miss GenSan Pageant, the Bodyfest Modeling Competition, and the Float Light Parade. Aside from food exhibitions and several other competitions, the festival also highlights the annual Karagatan Awards. This event, organized by the Tuna Festival Council and local government, honors "the unsung heroes of the fishing industry" by giving them awards.
    </string>
</resources>
